Guide to the Donald M. Goldstein Collection, 1886-2005 UA.90.F78
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- Photographs, XIII.
  - World War II, 2.
    - Rain of Ruin: A Photographic History of Hiroshima and Nagasaki
      - Published Images, 1945 (Box Photo 10, Folder 1-2)
        - Members of the Japanese delegation board USS Lansdowne (DD-486) at 6:33 A.M. on September 2, 1945, for the 1-hour-45-minute voyage to Missouri., 309.
        - An honor guard presents arms at Yokohama as Mac-Arthur arrives for the voyage to surrender site., 310.
          Buchanan lies moored at right.
        - Admiral Sir Bruce Fraser, the United Kingdom's signatory to the surrender, steps onto Missouri after the short hop from Duke of York., 311.
        - General Joseph W. Stillwell (left) talks to a group of American officers while awaiting the surrender ceremony., 312.
        - Missouri's graceful bow frames Mount Fuji., 313.
          Note anchor chain and Union Jack. Either Duke of York or King George V lies in the distance at left.
        - The scene on Missouri just moments before the surrender ceremony., 314.
        - Her crew mustered in dress whites, Missouri stands ready to receive the Japanese delegation on the morning of September 2, 1945., 315.
          Note the Gleaves-class destroyer (likely Buchanan) standing by on her starboard beam.
        - Missouri from astern. Note the Curtiss SC-1 Seahawk scout planes on her catapults., 316.
        - Accompanied by Nimitz, MacArthur strides by the barbette of Number 2 turret toward the cloth-bedecked mess table, on which lies the Instrument of Surrender., 317.
        - MacArthur and Nimitz board USS Missouri (BB-63) to receive the Japanese surrender September 2, 1945. [NH 49707], 318.
        - Missouri's welcoming party comes to attention and salutes as Foreign Minster Shigemitsu, visible at left in the top hat, struggles to board the battleship at 8:56., 319.
        - Shigemitsu's credentials. The Japanese were not asked to present them. [80-G-70150], 320.
        - Shigemitsu's credentials. The Japanese were not asked to present them., 321.
        - The Japanese delegation presents itself to MacArthur., 322.
          In the group are (front row left to right) Mamoru Shigemitsu, Foreign Minister; General Toshijiro Umezu, Chief of Staff; (second row Lt. Gen. Shinichi Miyazaki, Director of the 1st Department of the Army Division of General Headquarters; Katsuo Okazaki, Director General of the Central Liaison Office; RADM Sadatoshi Tomioke, Director of the 1st Department of the Navy Division of General Headquarters; Toshikazu Kase, Director of the 3rd Department of the Board of Information; Maj. Gen. Yatsuji Nagai, Army Staff Officer of General Headquarters; (third row) hidden, RADM Ichiro Yokoyama, Navy Minister; hidden Saburo Ohta, Director of the 3rd Department of the Central Liaison Office; Capt. Katsuo Shiba, Navy Staff Officer of General Headquarters; Col. Ichiji Sugita, army Staff Officer of General Headquarters. Lt. C. F. Wheeler took this and many Navy photographs from this vantage point. [80-G-348365]
        - At 9:02 A.M., MacArthur, representing all the Allied nations, steps to the microphone and addresses the gathering., 323.
          From his perch on Missouri's bridge, Navy photographer Lieutenant C.A. Poots preserved for posterity the entire ceremony, creating a unique record of one of history's truly memorable events.
        - At 9:04 A.M., the Japanese are invited to sign the Instrument of Surrender., 324.
          Confused as to where to sign, Shigemitsu fumbles for his fountain pen, while Kase points out the correct place on the English copy. The delegation appears somewhat more relaxed. Saburo Ohta in his white suit, hidden in 7-28, stands at left on the third row, hat in hand. Note the scaffolding at right, built for the military and press photographer.
        - Stooped over the table despite the discomfort of his artificial leg, Shigemitsu signs the Japanese copy of the surrender., 325.
        - At 9:06, General Umezu signs for Imperial General Headquarters., 326.
        - At 9:08, MacArthur signs for all the Allied nations while a solemn assembly of officers looks on., 327.
        - At 9:12, Nimitz signs the Japanese copy of the surrender for the United States of America while MacArthur looks on from behind the microphone., 328.
        - At 9:13, General Hsu Yung-chang signs for China., 329.
        - At 9:14, Admiral Sir Bruce Fraser signs for the United Kingdom., 330.
        - At 9:16, Lieutenant General Kuzma Nikolaivich Derevyenko signs for the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics., 331.
        - At 9:17, General Sir Thomas Blamey signs for Australia. [80-G-332707], 332.
        - At 9:18, Colonel L. Moore Cosgrave signs for Canada signed the Japanese copy; he inadvertently skipped one space, displacing the last four signatures – an error the Japanese caught at the last minute. [80-G-332708], 333.
        - At 9:20, General Jacques Leclerc signs for France., 334.
        - At 9:21, Admiral Conrad Helfrich signs for the Netherlands. Last to sign was Air Vice Marshall Sir L.M. Isitt for New Zealand., 335.
        - A nervous footnote to the ceremony. As Shigemitsu and Kase look on, Sutherland corrects the Japanese copy of the surrender, marred by the Canadian signatory's error., 336.
        - American aircraft appear over Missouri following the surrender ceremony., 337.
          Note the victory tally on the bridge and the thirty-star flag, the same banner raised by Commodore Perry at Tokyo on July 14, 1853. It was too fragile to fly, so was displayed on the bulkhead. [111-SC-211875; 111-SC-210644]
          Photo number: 7-43A-B
        - Naval aircraft fly over Missouri after the surrender., 338.
          Note the destroyers standing by to take off the press and dignitaries.
        - Aircraft over Ancon (AGC-4), hardy veteran of amphibious operations off Morocco, Sicily, Normandy, and Okinawa., 339.
        - The Japanese delegation receives honors as it leaves Missouri at the conclusion of the surrender ceremony shortly before 9:30., 340.
        - Japanese on Lansdowne return to Yokohama., 341.
          Note Saburo Ohta in his white suit, at center.
        - MacArthur departs Missouri at 9:58., 342.
        - Plaque affixed over the surrender site on the deck of Missouri in October 1945., 343.
        - The Instrument of Surrender that ended World War II [80-G-701058; 80-G-701057], 344.
          Photo number: 7-50A-B
        - Colonel Bernard Thielen presents the Instrument of Surrender to President Truman after escorting the document during its long flight from Japan., 345.
          Also present are (l-r): Secretary of the Navy James Forrestal, Secretary of War Henry Stimson, General George C. Marshall, Fleet Admiral Ernest J. King, Acting Secretary of State Dean Acheson, General A.A. Vandegrift, USMC, Fleet Admiral William D. Leahy, and Lieutenant General Ira C. Eaker.
        - Japanese soldiers returning to their Tokyo homes, pushing a cart loaded with their gear, passing one of the hundreds of demolished areas in the city., 346.
        - Lieutenant General Tomoyuki Yamashita (left center wearing dark coat and white shirt) is arraigned before the War Crimes Commission in Manila., 347.
          The members of this tribunal are (l-r): Brigadier General E.F. Bullens, Major General C.L. Sturdevant, Major General Russell B. Reynolds, Major General J.A. Lester, and Brigadier General W.G. Walker.
        - Helena Rodriguez testifies concerning a Japanese atrocity., 348.
          Prosecuting attorney is Captain Delmas Wamege.
        - Children orphaned in the bombing of Kumamoto pose with a nurse., 349.
        - Two women and a small child attend a Shinto memorial services held in the bank building for the blast victims., 350.
        - An Atomic bomb survivor awaits treatment at a temporary hospital., 351.
        - Blast victims rest on straw mats in a Hiroshima bank, Kango Ginku., 352.
          Navy lieutenant Wayne Miller took this and the following three photos.
        - A man rests while reading in the bank building., 353.
          Note the bowl and chopsticks beside his mat.
        - Flies cover everything in the makeshift hospital., 354.
        - A number of bombing victims – mostly soldiers occupy Hiroshima's main train station., 355.
        - Two nurses and a doctor treat less seriously burned individuals in Hiroshima's Red Cross Hospital., 356.
        - Many patients at the Red Cross Hospital had to be treated outside., 357.
        - A young man from Nagasaki exhibits scars typical of many burn victims., 358.
        - Note that while this man's clothing protected him in part, his shirt, open at the neck, exposed him to burns which resulted in the keliod on his chest., 359.
        - The road to recovery was difficult for the many who suffered serious burns around their joints., 360.
        - In the case of this woman, grafting was only partly successful and led to extensive scarring., 361.
        - Major General Orvil A. Anderson, head of the USSBS Military Analysis Division., 362.
        - Rear Admiral Ralph J. Ofstie, head of the USSBS Naval Analysis Division., 363.
          Shown here as a captain in February 1944, while commanding USS Essex (CV-9) during strikes on Truk.
        - Two American Strategic Bombing Survey officers examine damage in Hiroshima., 364.
          The Commercial Display Building is in the background.
        - A Japanese soldier walking through a leveled portion of Hiroshima., 365.
          Lieutenant Wayne Miller, USNR, took this picture during September 1945.
        - On September 26, 1945, Photographer's Mate Third Class George Almarez, USS Appalachian (AGC-1) snapped an attempt to return to normalcy in Hiroshima., 366.
        - Australian prisoners of war en route home., 367.
        - Nurses from the 308th General Hospital sleep on the ground pending construction of proper quarters., 368.
        - An Army delegation greets Danny Kaye at Hiroshima on October 25, 1945., 369.
        - Members of the Atomic Bomb Casualty Commission gather for a luncheon given by the assistant mayor of Hiroshima on December 6, 1946., 370.
          Kneeling (l-r) are a city official, Lieutenant F. Ullrich, Lieutenant J. Neel, Dr. Tsuzuki. Standing (l-r) are Mr. Saida, a city official, Colonel H. Johnson, Dr. R. S. Hinshaw, Dr. A. Brues, Dr. H. Volk, Dr Matsubayashi, Lieutenant Block, Dr. Omura.
        - Officers from the USSBS huddle together near ground zero and examine the devastation in Nagasaki., 371.
          Compare this scene with the left portion of the panorama in 5-33.
        - Survey personnel inspect a double-track railroad bridge lying across a small tributary of the Urakami River near ground zero., 372.
        - An American officer points to capitals on a wall of Urakami Cathedral from which two columns were blown away at left., 373.
          Note Chinzei School on the hill beyond.
        - First Lieutenant D.A. McGovern of Buffalo, New York (port of the newsreel pool), prepared to take some movie footage amid the devastation of Nagasaki., 374.
        - Nagasaki, spring 1946., 375.
          New shoots grow from a chestnut 2,000 feet from ground zero.
        - View looking north up the Urakami River toward Nagasaki on August 3, 1946., 376.
          Note new construction in the area east of the old Mitsubishi Steel and Armament Works. The wreckage of the plant has not yet been cleared.
        - Slowly, a portion of the cultural infrastructure of Hiroshima and Nagasaki experienced a resurrection., 377.
          Here, the rebuilt Urakami Church stands complete on May 29, 1949.
        - Two years after the explosion over Nagasaki, agricultural expert Takeo Furuno holds up a sesame stalk at left, grown in a field 300 yards from the hypocenter., 378.
          The results presaged human genetic disorders extending out for generations.
        - A portion of the command crew of the 509th Composite Group after the war, 379.
          (l-r): Major Van Kirk, navigator; Lieutenant James W. Anderson copilot (he actually flew in No. 91 on August 6, 1945); Major Ferebee, bombardier; Colonel Tibbets, pilot. Ferebee, looking substantially older, has shaved off his mustache.
        - The atomic bomb pilots and their bombardiers (l-r): Sweeney, Seaham, Ferebee, and Tibbets., 380.
        - Nagasaki pilot and copilot after the war – Captain Charles Albury (left; promoted from first lieutenant since the mission), and Major Sweeney., 390.
        - Enola Gay enjoys a spot on center stage at the National Air Fair at O'Hare Field in Chicago, July 3, 1949., 391.
          Present (l-r) are Mr. Carl Mitman of the Smithsonian Institution; Tibbets; Ferebee; and Major General Emmett J. O'Donnell.
        - In the 1952 movie Above and Beyond, Hollywood produced a mix of wartime romance and a great story of American ingenuity and heroics., 392.
          Note that Tibbets (Robert Taylor) has not yet been promoted to full colonel, an event which (in the movie) elicited a tantrum from the moody Mrs. Tibbets (Eleanor Parker).
        - A view looking across the Motoyasu River toward the Hiroshima Commercial Display Building., 393.
        - Exposed to the elements, the supporting framework of the dome slowly rusts away., 394.
        - Likewise open to the weather, the masonry walls crumble with the passage of time., 395.
        - Japanese tourists pause in front of the dome and ponder the past and future., 396.
        - Just across the Motoyasu River from the A-bomb Dome, youngsters cluster around the Peace Bell at Hiroshima., 397.
        - Solemn observes gather in the rain at the Children's Peace Monument., 398.
        - Atop the monolithic sculpture stands a young girl with a representation of an origami bird supported in her hands., 399.
        - Eerie and surreal, the Children's Peace Monument sculptures are reminiscent of the corpses found by the thousands in the aftermath of the explosions., 400.
        - Still farther south, the Memorial Monument for Hiroshima is dedicated to all victims of the first atomic bomb., 401.
        - The Memorial Monument with the Commercial Display Building ruin in the background. [Goldstein 30], 402.
        - The Memorial Monument is a popular place for reflection, and draws many groups of Japanese students, easily identified here by their school garb., 403.
        - The Hiroshima Peace memorial Museum houses a diverse collection of artifacts and photography from the bombing's aftermath., 404.
        - A child's jumper in the museum display. [Goldstein 31], 405.
        - A child's jacket shows the effect of the blast on individuals within a mile and a half of the hypocenter., 406.
          Those closer in frequently had clothing burned away or blown off. [Goldstein 8]
        - The crushed remains of bicycle recovered from the ruins of Hiroshima., 407.
        - The older generation, with physical and mental scars, and firsthand memories of the A-Bomb, dwindles with every passing year., 408.
        - Japanese schoolgirls at the memorial. [Goldstein 5], 409.
        - Younger generations have been inculcated with the history of the Hiroshima bombing from a very early age., 410.
      - Extras, 1939 - 1993 (Box Photo 10, Folder 3-6)
      - Negatives, undated (Box Photo 10, Folder 7-8)
      - Slides, 1993 (Box Photo 10, Folder 9)
      - Photocopied, 1945- 1952 (Box Photo 10, Folder 10)
    - Target Tokyo: The Story of the Sorge Spy Ring
      - Published Images, 1930s - 1945 (Box Photo 10, Folder 11)
        - The house at Adjikent near Baku where Richard Sorge was born., 1.
        - Richard at eight years with his father, Adolf Sorge., 2.
        - Richard Sorge as a young soldier during World War I., 3.
        - Sorge on his twenty-third birthday, October 1918., 4.
        - Sorge (at rear) in a hospital during World War I., 5.
        - Richard Sorge in October 1933 at the outset of his mission in Japan., 6.
        - Sorge's passport, 1937., 7.
        - Sorge during the period of his espionage ring in Tokyo, circa 1937., 8.
        - Sorge's second wife, Ykaterina ("Katcha") Maximova, standing over her two sisters., 9.
        - Façade of the German Embassy in Tokyo in 1938., 10.
        - Seiichi Ichijima, governor of Sugamo Prison., 11.
        - Anna Clausen., 12.
        - Max Clausen during period of espionage in Tokyo., 13.
        - Hanako Ishii, Sorge's companion for many years, with Professor Gordon Prange., 14.
          Ishii wrote a book on her life with Sorge.
        - Sample of Clausen's encoding work sheets., 15.
        - Max Clausen's radio sets: transmitter on left, receiver on right., 16.
        - Hotzumi Ozaki., 17.
        - Branko de Voukelitch., 18.
        - One of the last pictures taken of Richard Sorge., 19.
    - The Way it Was: Pearl Harbor, The Original Photographs
      - Published Images, 1930s - 1960s (Box Photo 10, Folder 12-22)
        - Admiral Isoroku Yamamoto, commander in chief, Combined Fleet, originator of the plan to attack Pearl Harbor., 1.
        - Rear Admiral Takijiro Onishi, chief of staff, 11th Air Fleet, 2.
        - Commander Minoru Genda, air staff officer, 1st Air Fleet, 3.
        - Vice Admiral Chuichi Nagumo, commander in chief, 1st Air Fleet, 4.
        - Rear Admiral Ryunosuke Kusaka, chief of staff, 1st Air Fleet, 5.
        - Rear Admiral Tamon Yamaguchi, commander, 2nd Carrier Division, 6.
        - Rear Admiral Chuichi Hara, commander, 5th Carrier Division, 7.
        - Vice Admiral Gunichi Mikawa, commander, 3rd Battleship Division, 8.
        - Rear Admiral Sentaro Omori, commander, 1st Destroyer Squadron, 9.
        - Rear Admiral Shigeyoshi Miwa, commander, 3rd Submarine Squadron, 10.
        - Commander Mitsuo Fuchida, commander, 1st Air Fleet, 11.
        - Admiral Husband Kimmel, commander in chief, Pacific Fleet (center), flanked by his operations officer, Captain Walter Delany (left), and his chief of staff, captain William Ward Smith (right), 12.
        - Admiral James Richardson, Kimmel's predecessor, 13.
        - Rear Admiral Claude Bloch, commander of the 14th Naval District, 14.
        - Vice Admiral William Pye, commander, Battle Force, 15.
        - Vice Admiral William Halsey, commander, Aircraft, Battle Force, 16.
        - Rear Admiral Patrick Bellinger, commander, Patrol Wing Two, 17.
        - Lt. General Walter Short, commanding general, Hawaiian Department (left), with Kimmel (right), Captain Lord Louis Mountbatten (center), Major General Frederick Martin, and Bellinger in September 1941., 18.
        - Major General Frederick Martin, commanding general, Hawaiian Air Force, 19.
        - Brigadier General Jacob Rudolph, commanding general, 18th Bombardment Wing, 20.
        - Brigadier General Howard Davidson, commanding general, 14th Pursuit Wing, 21.
        - The aircraft carrier Akagi, flagship of the Pearl harbor Strike Force, 22.
          Page number: 8-9
        - Kaga, companion to Akagi in the 1st Carrier Division, 23.
        - Soryu, lead ship in the 2nd Carrier Division, 24.
        - Hiryu of the 2nd Carrier Division, 25.
        - Shokaku, flagship of the 5th Carrier Division, 26.
        - Zuikaku of the 5th Carrier Division, 27.
        - Hiei, flagship of the Pearl Harbor Support Force, 28.
        - Kirishima of the Pearl Harbor Support Force, 29.
        - The heavy cruiser Tone, 30.
        - The heavy cruiser Chikuma, 31.
        - The light cruiser Abukuma, flagship of the 1st Destroyer Squadron, 32.
        - Isokaze, a destroyer, 33.
          Page number: 12-13
        - Shiranuhi takes on fuel from a tanker, 34.
        - A "Zero" from Akagi, 35.
        - A "Val" from Akagi, 36.
        - A "Kate" from Akagi, 37.
        - Type 91 Kai Model 2 torpedoes rest on board Akagi's flight deck. Note Hiryu in the background., 38.
        - Type 99 Number 80 Mark III bomb, 39.
        - California (BB-40), moored to TenTen Pier in Pearl Harbor in August 1941, 40.
        - Oklahoma (BB-37) at left and Nevada (BB-36) lie moored to the quays along Ford Island on 3 November 1941, 41.
        - Utah (AG-16) being painted into Measure 1 camouflage at Mare Island in 1941, 42.
        - New Orleans (CA-32), 43.
        - St. Louis (CL-49) in the summer of 1941, 44.
        - The light cruiser Detroit (CL-8), 45.
        - MacDonough (DD-351), a Farragut class destroyer, 46.
        - Phelphs (DD-360), a Porter class destroyer, 47.
        - Conyngham (DD-371), a Mahan class destroyer, 48.
        - Ralph Talbot (DD-390), a Gridley class destroyer, 49.
          Page number: 16-17
        - Montgomery (DM-17) moored with 3 other minecraft in Pearl Harbor in early 1941, 50.
        - Flush-deck destroyers Chew (DD-106), at left, and Ward (DD-139) at Hilo in July 1941., 51.
        - Dolphin (SS-169), 52.
        - Oglala (CM-4), 53.
        - The hospital ship Solace (AH-5), 54.
        - The Curtiss P-40B, 55.
        - The Curtiss P-36A, 56.
          Page number: 18-19
        - The Douglas B-18 "Bolo", 57.
        - The Boeing B-17D "Flying Fortress", 58.
        - Douglas A-20A "Havoc", 59.
        - The Grumman F4F-3 "Wildcat", 60.
        - Douglas SBD-1 "Dauntless", 61.
        - Vought SB2U-3 "Vindicator", 62.
        - Consolidated PBY-5 "Catalina", 63.
          Page number: 20-21
        - An OS2U-3 "Kingfisher" alongside its ship, Arizona, during exercises on 6 September 1941., 64.
        - Grumman J2F "Duck" from the Navy utility squadron VJ-1, 65.
        - A VJ-1 Sikorsky JRS-1 amphibian, 66.
          Page number: 22-23
        - A 5-inch, 25-caliber AA mount, 67.
        - A 5-inch, 38-caliber AA mount, 68.
        - A 3-inch, 50-caliber AA mount, 69.
        - A 3-inch, 23-caliber AA mount, 70.
        - The 1.1-inch quadruple heavy machine-gun mount, 71.
        - Browning water-cooled, .50-caliber machine gun, 72.
        - Pearl Harbor on 31 October 1941 with Ford Island at the center, the Navy Yard, submarine Base, and fuel oil tank farms at the left, and Hickman Field beyond the Navy Yard., 73.
          Page number: 24-25
        - The Pearl Harbor Navy Yard on 13 October 1941, 74.
        - Drydock No. 1 and Arizona in 1932, 75.
        - Pearl Harbor's submarine base, 76.
        - Ford island on 10 November 1941 with Naval Air Station hangars at lower left, 77.
        - Pennsylvania, flagship of the Pacific Fleet, lies moored to TenTen Pier on 11 August 1941, as seen from the Argonne, 78.
        - Pearl Harbor from Argonne's bridge on 11 August 1941, showing West Virginia, Arizona, and Oklahoma, 79.
        - The light cruise St. Louis (right) rests beside Montgomery (right) and Breese in the Navy Yard's Repair Basin in October 1941, 80.
        - Hickam Field in October 1941, with the Hale Makai Aircrew Barracks just behind the hangar line and Hawaiian Air Depot hangars at the bottom, 81.
          Page number: 28-29
        - Colonel William Farthing, commanding officer, Hickam Field, 82.
        - Hickam Field's main gate in the late 1930s, 83.
        - Wheeler Field in October 1935, 84.
        - Colonel Williwam Flood, 85.
        - Wheeler Field's Noncommissioned Officers' Club, 86.
        - Bellows Field, 87.
          Page number: 30-31
        - Lt. Colonel Leonard Weddington, 88.
        - Bellows Field's main gate, 89.
        - Haleiwa Field on Oahu's northwest coast, 90.
        - Kaneohe Bay on 1 October 1941; note the unfinished hangar, 91.
        - Commander Harold "Beauty" Martin, 92.
        - Pearl Harbor naval Air Station, 10 October 1941, at Lt. Comdr. Kakuichi Takahashi saw it at 0755, 7 December 1941, 93.
        - Captain James Shoemaker, 94.
        - Ewa Marine Corps Air Station in October 1941, 95.
        - Lt. Colonel Claude Larkin, 96.